[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
all right welcome everybody to
another session here at the stoda stoa
uh you might have noticed that i am not
peter lindbergh
but um i've been collaborating with him
here at the stoa
um uh for well i think close to the
close to the beginning of uh the
sessions here
so i'm going to be running a little
session today with david collins who i'm
going to intro in just a minute
but before i do that i want to tell you
a little bit about the side view which
is the
website and publication that i run um
i'll tell you a little bit about our
structure and if you're new to the stoa
i'll just go over a little bit of kind
of the protocol
of discussion questions and things like
that so
we're going to go for about an hour
we're scheduled until 6 pm
and in that time
dave is going to talk for about 15 to 20
minutes
i also have prepared a few questions
that i want to ask dave just
three or four questions so in this first
half hour
or so dave will be speaking
we'll have a little bit of a back and
forth um then we're going to open it up
in the second half
for all of you if you have questions or
um comments or just want to jump in the
dialogue
in one way or another that second half
will be
for the larger discussion the way we
usually do it here
is that you can either signal that you
have
a question during the period or
you can while we're talking while dave
is presenting while we're having our
dialogue if something comes up for you
feel free to drop your question or your
comment
into the chat box and then when we get
to the general discussion we can go
through those
and start to address those questions at
that time so
in the first half it'll be mostly dave
and i talking
but again if something does come up for
you
please feel free to put it in the chat
box there and then
you can also indicate to me or in the
chat there
if you would like to read the question
yourself or
if you would just like me as the
moderator to read it for you you can do
either way so let's get going here um
like i said i run a publication called
the side view the side view is a
website it's a journal it's a podcast
it's an event series uh centered around
the idea of
practice philosophical practice
contemplative practice spiritual
practice but also
practice of perception of
any kind really so we're also interested
in designers and scientists and athletes
and engineers
people who have trained themselves
trained their perception trained their
awareness trained their attention
to see the world in a skillful way to be
able to engage and act
within the world with some kind of
skillful means
and the side view the meaning behind the
title is just to say
instead of looking at the uh the
finished books the finished works of art
the finished theories and ideas
uh behind different philosophical or
contemplative
movements or traditions we look at it
from the side right to look at the
practices
that create the people who have those
insights
and so i launched this website um
just over two years ago maybe two and a
half years ago
and it really was one of those
situations
where i didn't i didn't know what was
going to happen when i launched the site
i had this idea
um and you know they always say when you
build something like this
you're going to attract a certain group
of people who kind of responds to the
call
you know if you build it they will come
and then who is they
i had no idea but david collins was one
of those people
and he just kind of showed up into my
orbit and um
ever since then we've had a very rich
rich
rich dialogue about the nature of
not just philosophical practice but uh
religious contemplative spiritual
meditative practice
and the the interrelations among all of
those
different disciplines and different
traditions and not just within one
tradition but across traditions
so i'm happy to introduce dave if you
don't know him
he holds a master's degree
in contemplative theology another
masters
in world religion with the focus on
buddhist studies from harvard
he also has a phd in clinical psychology
so you're going to hear
in the way that he talks a a very sort
of
living sense of not just the academic
and the scholarly
and not just the the sort of practice
oriented side of
contemplation but also this this sort of
very practical and clinical and
therapeutic
dimension to everything that he's doing
um
so really he's drawing from a rich
training a rich
history and that writing took him to
study cross-cultural parallels in
contemplative practices mostly if you
know
the anonymous author of the christian
contemplative book the cloud of
unknowing
dave has actually written quite a bit
about that text
in relation to uh dogen's
zen buddhist meditation instructions so
there's some interesting parallels there
that dave's research has been drawing
from and
as i mentioned he's also an adept
meditator
uh having studied at the san francisco
zen center
and uh insight meditation at spirit rock
um and so he's written a few articles
for us um
over these past few years if you look in
the chat box
i've dropped his the links to the
website
and to his essays in particular you can
see
the first one there is about that book
the cloud of unknowing
the second one is a is a very rich
history about um
how how mindfulness meditation was
adopted and taking up
in the western context both as a kind of
assimilation of certain buddhist
practices but also the way it's shown up
in clinical practice and then the last
one
um is the piece that i actually asked
dave to talk about today
which is the piece on socrates the essay
is called the contemplatives
socrates and i wanted
dave to talk about this piece a little
bit because there's
there's really an untold history that
that is supported by the scholarship and
supported by
um our you know sort of best
understanding of what
this greek philosopher socrates what his
life was like what his practices were
like in fact
and this richer more complex story that
dave is going to tell us about
really has a lot more to do with
socrates as a as a contemplative
practitioner
and not just this kind of advocate for
uh reason and dialectical questioning
and uh you know erudite definitions and
these kinds of things that you might
learn
uh that that a sort of intro to
philosophy
course might teach you about socrates so
i think it's actually important to learn
this history
and so with that i'm going to pass it
over to dave
and tell us a little bit about the
contemplative socrates
so please welcome dave thanks adam
um despite as adam has listed
having an altogether embarrassing amount
of education
um i'm not going to mention the fact
that i don't consider myself
particularly a socrates expert
i will say though that saying
you're not going to say something
mentioning the fact that you're not
going to mention something
is a rhetorical move and has a name
the name for saying you're not going to
say something is
an apophasis
technically apophasis means negation or
denial
in rhetoric examples like uh in a debate
we shall not mention his many crimes
well you just mentioned it that's an
apophasis
also saying something by saying what
it's not
my grades aren't all that bad you said
your grades are good
but you said it by saying they're not
bad again
rhetorical move an apophasis
contemplative applications
apophasis and the adjective apophatic
came to be applied to those sorts of
traditions
and practices which
well the latin word often used or
phrases via negativa the negative way
the way of
letting go the way of stepping out from
under conceptual
constructed discursive thoughts
and coming into contact with something
more
simple more basic more original
more honest more humble
the words get big apathic contemplative
tradition
but it's about something
quintessentially
simple there is this is now my
phrasing a miracle going on
there really is and it's everything
and it behooves us to reconnect
with what's always already here before
we're so
identified with some of our cognitive
maps our philosophical
opinions our discursive uh frameworks
for what's real
what's important so the letting go
the getting simple the questioning
of our frameworks and concepts
is um what's gestured at by the
word uh apophasis in the contemplative
application um
i didn't know a lot about socracy i'm
working on on a book
looking uh based off the uh dissertation
that adam
referenced uh looking at cross-cultural
parallels
in contemplative uh practices
and in the case of the folks i uh
focused on for the dissertation the the
cloud author in
england 14th century christian and on
the opposite side of the world
uh dogen in in japan very different
cultural frameworks very different
theological vocabularies
but they're doing very similar
practices very similar meditative
techniques
and it tickles my mind in the case of
those two authors each
over time went back and made edits to
their original instructions
and they made the same edits
they're learning the same thing
the edits are in the direction of
something even more simple
the words get complicated even more
ontological
rather than something conceptual rather
than something intentional
it's about a naked experience of being
that's the cloud author's language or or
an embodiment a participation
in suchness will be the zen
language so i was interested in looking
at
how the cloud author inherited that
practice that discourse and going back
to
some of the beginnings in the west
with plato and then of course before
plato
uh socrates and to my
delight um came to realize
that socrates was a deeply
religious human being popularly
he's he's understood as sort of the
parent of rational
philosophic enterprise in in the west
um so much of our
popular sort of inheritance of how to
think about
philosophy is shaped by
his follower um plato
and even more by plato student aristotle
much of the way the word philosophy
philosopher is constructed
conceptualized
is aristotle then projecting back
to plato socrates and the so-called
pre-socratics as a quick example
plato will gesture towards a
ancient quarrel between the philosophers
and the poets the myth tellers
the musicians but plato made that
up there was no such ancient quarrel
in part because plato himself is using
that word philosophy
for a first time in the way we end up
understanding that word and some of the
folks who do
get understood to be uh quote-unquote
pre-socratic
philosophers were poets they were
writing
poetry and parmenides
is a good example
plato i mean uh socrates
was um
put into motion embodied
exemplified this sort of questioning of
our conceptual
constructs our presumptions
our inherited values our habitual
frameworks
plato uh again socrates was all about
asking annoying questions
getting people to reflect on things like
what is
piety what is courage
what is temperance moderation
and as often as not especially as as
portrayed in
um the dialogues from from plato uh
the folks he'd asked these questions
would end up realizing they don't really
know
and would end up in the greek word is a
aporia
an an impasse being at a loss to know
what to say or think
that examination of our assumptions
that interrogation of our concepts
and i'll not be able to resist referring
to the cloud
again in middle english the language of
the cloud author
the way you spelled the word concept
with c-o-n-c
[Music]
a conceit and i always
am reminded of that when when looking at
um
interrogations of thought concepts are
our our conceits
the the notions that we have a certain
investment in
and tend not to to question
socrates was all about asking questions
he purported he acted as if
he were ignorant in order to have people
explain to them what's real what's
valuable
what do they live their life by
that kind of ignorance that's kind of uh
interrogation of thought structures
puts into motion not that others weren't
doing it but he does it
in a way that ends up having immense
influence on the rest of uh western
culture puts into motion what in for
example the neoplatonus
like platinus becomes a a meditative
process
of letting go of thoughts
of coming to rest in what uh platinus
will speak of as an
unseeing or an unknowing
um similar in the east to the zen
language about non-thinking a practice
of what's here before we have an idea
of what's here it's not so much blanking
your mind
as as as getting undistracted
being less identified with mere
notions and ideas
another aspect of socrates
uh spirituality and let me interject
here
in his time his part of the world they
didn't have a word which directly
corresponds to our word
religion a closest word is
is piety and it's very much
connected with practices
athens of his time um you
typically have a couple of altars in
your home
to the gods you'd pour a libation
a little bit of of your drink and
offerings to the gods before you had
a drink or a meal you and your customer
in the marketplace
would invoke the gods to bless be
present to
sanction your business transaction
festivals ceremonies every week or so
in athens as we don't know exactly how
phaley's
meant an early thinker but
the phrase fits well for this culture
everything is full of gods they were
mindful of
of having a transaction
uh interaction with divine forces
all the time but it was largely
uh performative it was largely uh
about how you did things it was largely
about following
ceremonies and traditionals but
traditions
and not to do so much with having a
creed
or set i believe
orientation as part of that the the
greeks
were open to other deities other
divinities
um from other cultures and adopting them
if the community if the
assembly
was into it approved of it
a problem with socrates
is that he had his own style he did
things his own way
and he had in particular something like
a guardian angel
the greek word for it is daimonian um
it translated sort of a divine thing
and described different ways by
different uh folks
but it was a sort of um plato describes
it as a
as a voice oh and xenophon
describes it as a kind of a sense of an
omen
that uh and plato's characterization
would tell socrates not to do something
if it wasn't
a good idea uh xenophon says it also
prompted him to
do some things like um give advice to
certain people
he had it since a childhood
so this paragon of
popularly conceived rationality
had a spirit had something he was in
conversation with so to speak but it was
his own
it wasn't sanctioned by the populist
and given his potentially
more than potentially given his
disruptive manner
of asking folks what's really
real what really matters and
disturbing to the sort of
mainstream he was getting young people
to
question their parents about their
values and
styles and habits so along with having
a divine thing that
wasn't approved of by the community in
a time in place where spirituality was
very
much a communal engagement
he was doing his own thing in such a way
that
enough people thought that was
disruptive
or even dangerous that he was charged
with
um corrupting the youth and
uh introducing new gods and enough of
the athenians
felt that was unacceptable
it got him condemned and executed
but again how
we see philosophy i liked in uh
the the talk of the store the other
night um james cars and uh
john vervecchi the way john used the
word
reverence reminded me of a way
we can interact with the fillo the love
word in philosophy a reverence for
wisdom which is a different thing than a
sort of conceptual
decision or arguing about propositions
and and
claims it was very much as as
adam alluded to earlier a practice an
experiential engagement
it was and this is a whole nother talk
but
my sense of looking at what philosophy
meant
socrates didn't use that word very much
and it was just sort of vaguely
uh sophistication or cultured thinking
before plato and in plato
it ends up being i very much the more i
look at plato the more i sense
he was doing religion in another way
he was cultivating
advocating looking past appearances
to the miracle that everything
participates in
which he called the good as
a transformative dialogic
ultimately spiritual engagement
later aristotle has a more
rationalistic take and we get a split
again to me it looks like plato's doing
another kind of religion
the split between the way we understand
religion
and we understand philosophy kind of
gets in motion with
with aristotle notwithstanding some of
the the practice
transformative engagements of the stoics
or the
um certainly in the the neoplatonus
they're doing meditation plate
platinus is a is a as a
stone cold contemplative
um one last
comment i'll make this wasn't in the
essay so i didn't know what to do with
it
but i've been thinking about some more
it's some 20 years later
after his his his death his execution
he's given hemlock poison he takes it
dies
some 20 years later or so uh plato does
an account of that event
in the the fido and
socrates he has socrates last words be
krito one of his his followers friends
we owe the god esclepius a
rooster make sure you get one
don't forget and then he dies
what is going on there he had previously
asked the jailer
when the jailer executioner brings him
the cup
of poison whether he could do a libation
do a spiritual
uh mini sacrifice offer a little bit of
it up
to the gods and the geneva says no you
can't there's
just the right amount for the for what
needs to happen
so instead of pouring the libation as a
spiritual act
socrates does a prayer
takes the medicine covers himself up
gets ready to die
and then as a kind of uh afterthought
says
we owe the goddess kept us a rooster
make sure you get one
one of the characteristic features of
socrates
he didn't write anything down everything
we know about him comes from other folks
who
wrote of him and a lot of what came
down we've lost a lot of it but what we
do have
aristophanes writes a satiric body play
about him
xenophon does an apology um
does a symposium and then does some
other accounts of
socrates life but plato is the most
creative
and had the most impact but each of
these folks
understood socrates a different way
and that's my sense that that's a
characteristic that that tells us
something about
what it was like he got people
individually in touch with what most
matters to them what they most valued
what they were most personally
reoriented towards to to appreciate
and pursue and this comes through in a
rather dramatic way in different
interpretations of those last words
we owe asclepius a rooster
asclepius is the god of healing
nietzsche and others
said opined that socrates
wants to offer the god of healing a
a gift in recognition for the release
from the disease of having a body
the god of healing deserves thanks
because he's getting rid of his body
a contemporary um scholar
named glenn most um
this this seems a bit outlandish to me
but his take
is that like the allusion to the swan
song which is also in the fido
the swans sing beautifully at their
death because they know they're going to
apollo they get a kind of a
telepathic understanding of what's going
on glenn most suggests
that at the very end socrates became
clairvoyant
and saw that plato had recovered
from a sickness plato's not present at
the end because he's too sick to be
there
seems a bit far-fetched to me
but another uh author who i don't know
much more
except for this piece he did name colin
west
points out that asclepius is not just
the um
god of healing by extension he's the god
of
medicine and the word for medicine
is the same word for poison
pharmacon which from which of course we
get pharmaceutical
um and that he's
somehow thankful for this
event this medicinal
he's reverent towards his poison
and a reason let's fight by extension
and i'm going to close here
that kind of resonates for me i've often
used this um
example of experience from my childhood
so much of contemplative material so
much of what also gets dubbed
mysticism um has a kind of
abstract or mystagogic association
um i've studied it up and down i'm still
learning and i've done decades of
of meditation practice
but a way i often uh use
to a story often used to kind of gesture
towards my sense of what's a core
of contemplative experience i went
through what it's like to die
as a kid i'm seven years old
i'm drowning in a crowded pool but
they don't see me and i'm underwater i
hit the bottom i'm there long enough
that i go through what it's like to die
that way i lost consciousness
i'm gone my little brother sees me
tells my mom my mom screams the
lifeguard jumps in
pulls me out i'm not breathing i'm blue
he gives me mouth-to-mouth resuscitation
my poor mother who's got some medical
training
did not like the signs but i came back
and when i'm coming back into awareness
i'm vomiting through my mouth and my
nose
into vomit that's already there in the
grass before i became conscious
everything hurt everything ached
and it was utterly beautiful
the fact that anything at all was going
on was its own worth of wonder before i
could remember my name
the fact that anything was happening was
enough
was its own worth now this is my
own the way in which socrates moves me
he moved people in different ways but i
wonder about that
sense of his gratitude even
for the experience of taking
the farmicon taking the medicine slash
poison an appreciation for the fact that
anything at all
is going on so that's the talk
thanks dave it's really rich terrain
that you're
taking us through here um
you said a number of things that
i think if you haven't dug into the
material and you haven't thought about
it
um too much or thought about it from
this perspective
um you've raised some points that would
raise some points that would raise some
eyebrows
is one way of putting it i think and i
think
um a lot of this comes from the fact
that
we're used to thinking of like
reason or rationalism and philosophy as
kind of a method of
rationalism uh as like one pole
of activity and religion and
spirituality is like another
poll um and i think the controversial
part
isn't that in ancient times those two
polls were much closer together in a
kind of integral way that's
that's kind of um historically
established and just sort of the case
right like people readily accept that
but what people in modern times want to
extract as sort of the gold
of socrates and plato is is precisely
the
rationality and the reason over and
against that kind of religiosity and as
you mentioned
religiosity religion religious practice
isn't a way they would have framed it at
that time
but when we look at it it looks more
like contemplative practice
or at least related to contemplative
practice reason as
nested within contemplative practice
than something that would
oppose those two things um but so what i
want to do first is just
uh draw out like the other poll
the the the the other a person who's
arguing for
nearly the opposite of what you're
arguing and
that person is john cooper um he's a
fantastic scholar
right he's like scholar of the first
order um
no qualms with the quality of
scholarship you know i this is a person
who's
whose texts i learned from a lot he's
also studying these ancient greek texts
plato and
stoicism and so forth but he's written
this book pursuits of wisdom where he
he actually takes this up as a theme and
there he's arguing against um
pierre hedoe and pierre hedoe's vision
of philosophy as a way of life her
philosophy is spiritual exercise and i
hear what you're saying is
much closer to hadeau than to cooper
but i want to read you this passage from
cooper and then ask you a question about
it
and so here's what he says in his book
pursuits of wisdom
cooper says the essential core of
philosophy is a certain
specifically and recognizably
philosophical style
of logical reasoned argument and
analysis
one must take with utmost seriousness
that what the ancient philosophers
following socrates's innovative league
are pro
proposing is that we live our lives from
some set of argued through
rationally worked out rationally grasped
and rationally defended ideas about the
world and one's own place within it a
philosophical way of life is therefore
in fundamental ways quite a different
thing
from any religious way of life
so my question for you here is
there's there's a certain sense of of of
reason and rationality
and a certain sense of religion
operating in
cooper's analysis here um which i think
is sort of more the mainstream view
um but i want to ask you how i how might
we think
differently of reason and rationality
and religion and how i how are we
supposed to think the relationship
between the two
so on the one hand um again
notwithstanding my
ridiculous amount of education i
went to school and then to the
monasteries
wanting to know what is most
important what is most valuable in being
alive
and i'll approach teachings texts
philosophies with a very pragmatic
interest how can this help me
appreciate being alive
part of that then lends to
uh realization as you alluded to earlier
the side view
our sense of rationality our
understanding and construction of what
religion is
our understanding construction of
philosophy is
comes from somewhere those have
histories those are generated events
and as a sort of parable
um it would be too long to to to go into
real uh
detail to sufficiently explain it but um
so much of contemplative practice is
appreciating the miracle of
any and everything the way it is here
and now
the associations of mysticism with like
say altered states
um is is a bit overdrawn but i've done
so
i've done some altered trade work for
the state's work
through old school buddhist uh genres
absorptions synthetic altered states
they occur in a sequence they are
remarkable
the buddhists will say don't get too
enamored of them just having sweet
experiences
to the point but having some uh
restoration having some recreation
but also just getting some further
insight in what the mind is capable of
is is sort of their worth following
10-day retreat
altered states really profound i mean
really
remarkable beautiful tear
evoking wonder in a set
sequence uh they're more than this but
standard four states
they unfold one after the other
following attendant retreat doing that
i was doing it in my sleep
i was waking up at night in the middle
of the sequence together with what i'm
going to kind of
metaphorically call a body memory of
having done the first couple before i
woke up
what that tells me
like a side view of our our historically
generated notions of what's rational
what's religious
our very identification with ourselves
in terms of our waking state our waking
cognitive process comes from somewhere
some part of me knows how to sleep some
part of me knows how to do
waking some part of me knows how to do
the jaundice whether i'm asleep or awake
so it's a little bit of a roundabout
reply
but two points to repeat our sense of
rationality is a generated phenomenon
it's booted up and two
we have the unfortunate um
propensity to presume that's
the end-all and be-all that's the
starting point and the end point that's
all there is to us
is this this rational logical
argumentative
mode and in the last couple of centuries
in the west especially that's
had a sad preeminence it does us a lot
of good
if and when we remember it's a tool it's
a utility
but if instead we make an idol out of it
that that's the only way to be
a human being and to know verities and
uh ascertain values
uh then we've uh sold ourselves short
that's great dave thanks for that um i'm
actually gonna
shift over to
the questions in the comments just
because i see that
hunter has a a couple of questions kind
of tied together that actually address
some of the directions i was about to go
in anyway so
i'm just looking at the time and
thinking maybe we can pass it off to
to a general discussion hunter did you
want to ask that question yourself or do
you want me to read it
um i'd be happy to jump in okay go ahead
um i just would like to try to
disentangle
the ancient sense of religion from the
modern sense
and to me the biggest confounding factor
is
dogma and so i wonder if you have any
um anything to add about that and it's
it's coercion upon you know
anyone who adheres to a given religion
yeah um it's interesting to me the
uh greeks and generations after uh
socrates and plato
became increasingly acquainted with the
hebrew scriptures
and called them philosophers that they
had an ancient
wisdom they are still wisdom is about
what enhances our appreciation of of
life
but throughout the centuries throughout
cultures there's to oversimplify only a
little
a a inveterate tendency
human beings have that when they find
something useful and valuable
there's there's the propensity to think
this is the only way
it's done and to make an
idol out of it to to uh
identify with the discerning
characteristics of it
and too often to become as your word
dogmatic about
it presumptuous about it conceded about
it
and to lose touch with the sort of
humble
original practical experiential
connection
with what was of worth and wonder in the
genesis of the thing
i have a presbyterian friend who's a bit
of a cut up
um but sharp as a attack
um and i asked him one time you know the
so much in the protestant
uh ethos is my understanding of this is
you have a conversion experience and and
you're done
and he says i feel like we need a
conversion experience
every day to overthrow
our conceits to overthrow getting too
comfortable
in our potentially dogmatic
uh decisions about what's what
i i really appreciate um i just
typed in the chat i can't help myself
but um just appreciate
how you re-linked back toward
the word conceit that you mentioned
earlier and
and how that links to preconceptions and
assumptions
and that's something that that we should
all
throw throw to the ditch if we can
because
yeah it's full of lots of errors a bar
from from your language um
relink is an etymological
uh meaning meaningful religion
to reconnect
that's great okay we got another one
from
nathan nathan did you want me to read it
or do you want to read it
i can uh read it um i guess i
one thing that sort of struck me was um
the mode in which um socratic inquiry
was undertaken you know both in socrates
as well
and also his disciples in the form of
violence
and there's a great book um i think
priebus the plato by havelock
that actually is in some ways kind of a
side view
of what was happening in ancient greek
culture at the time the shift from the
oral
culture of where people were feeding you
know
memory to writing things down and
he argued that the significance of his
philosophy was
trying to preserve this kind of oral
dialectic of interrogation
of these questions about what is justice
what is piety
and then then to this dialectical
engagement but provoking an insight
about the true nature of reality um
and so but this so this is the media
ecology you know in the ancient greek
world
and now that we live in the world of uh
communication
um can can the internet consume
serve as a vehicle for types of
contemplative practices
um like the uh like socrates practice
um you know because i think there is
both a promise
and apparel you know from the different
shifts from the ways in which we
communicate
you know information and trying to
hopefully promote you know
so you may know um socrates himself was
uh cherry about writing
he felt there was too much of the
potential that you alluded to
to merely hanging out with the words and
no longer having the lived
dialogic interpersonal uncovery and
discovery
and experiential engagement
um plato reflects that
in he writes dialogues people are
talking to each other they're having
conversations they're questioning each
other
even in parties um socrates gets
shown up as not knowing what he's
talking about in in
in the uh his uh talking about the forms
which incidentally uh is worth
remembering so much the time
we ascribe to plato this dogmatic
metaphysics about the forms and
everything participating in them
there was something he's exploring and
in parmenides uh
uh he tells socrates you know this
doesn't make any damn sense
but i'm reminded um
a little uh overly clunky
to me so much of this comes down to
an adverbial matter how we
do what we do how we be the miracle
that we are how we engage with one
another
artistically poetically transformatively
and i think the the resources are
amazing
and at the same time it
requires that sort of personal
engagement
i was so moved the the the the storm
meeting the other night
how much fun john fervecki seems to be
having with his
explorations and how content james cars
seems to be it's an experiential
transformative
how they are enjoying
their discourse their expirations
so i'll leave it at that
great uh dan did you have a question did
you want to type it or
did you want to just ask i can just ask
thanks
um the i really liked your quote before
where you said everything was full of
gods
that's a a very intriguing line
and recently uh in our meetings here in
florida
i found it uh very interesting that
people like discussing
that ancient form uh that you know god
nature logos and we've also been talking
about spinoza so i wanted to ask for you
ask you since the ancient times are
there any other authors or great
thinkers
who also discussed this idea
and um can you recommend anyone
so the folks i'm most familiar with are
the ones who
are are conservatively
engaged with contemplative practices
and in our part of the world through the
centuries that's
usually come under the rubric of
spiritual and religious
writers um although i already mentioned
um
um platinus
for whom whether it's philosophy or
whether it's religion
isn't the question he's doing something
transformative he's doing something
practical and experiential
he influences uh christian theologians
as they come to sort of have hegemony
in in the culture of folks like gregory
of nissa
and then uh the so-called
pseudo-dionysius the art alphaguite
uh who's very much influenced by
proclass also a neoplatonic philosopher
um ivagrius
uh john scottis regina um the cloud of
unknowing
john of the cross in our day
the centering prayer movement
there's a thread through all of those
figures and there are other ways to do
transformative practice there are other
styles of
of contemplative and mystical uh
experiential process but it's not hard
to find folks doing very similar
questioning of assumptions looking to
reconnect
with what's always already here the
miracle of living
being before we have a philosophy before
we have religion before we have a notion
about it
i'm reminded in the buddhist tradition
of an iconic archetypal
image on the eve on the night on the
verge of his awakening
um the buddha is sitting under the
enlightenment tree
and uh the demons realize if he wakes up
they're gonna be out of business
so they're interested in knocking him
off course
they come in with all sorts of uh
displays and distractions
um and finally just ask
by what authority what what like gives
you right what
is your um
[Music]
what makes it okay who speaks for you
and what you're doing here
and in reply the buddha just reaches
down and touches the earth
what's already true before i have a
philosophy
before i make up notions about it
reaching down and touching
the ground human beings have done that
since forever
as long as they've been human beings and
you can find them in different cultures
in different
times
okay i think we have time for probably
one more
alf do you want to ask your question
sure thanks david uh sorry if you
covered this in the article the link
didn't work from the last
show but i was wondering if you could
connect
zen awakening and socrates idea of
transformation
socrates kind of debated with a natural
philosophy because it could point to
logic and some truth but wouldn't
provide transformation
i was wondering if both of their ideas
of transformation from
zen to socrates are they both a form of
i don't know mind but with a
participatory knowing
so we get a sense
a kind of inference of how
profound a wise
and even loving person socrates was as
much as he was also
a nuisance in a nudge
by the fact that of the major
philosophic
practice schools
almost all of them traced their
inspiration to socrates
the cynics the stoics the plagueness
indirectly the uh aristotelians
the syringes the um uh
he serenade hedonists and vironic
skeptics
they've got different discourses and
different practices
but they're all inspired they're all
provoked and that gives me a sense that
socrates was
touching something living he was hitting
a nerve
people couldn't
some of them did ignore him walk away
don't get into it but that speaks to me
as something
uh experiential something personal
something
something something vital and again we
can get different languages different
words different labels for it
but just that sense of questioning
i'm thinking of the moment in the
documentary movie of the talking heads
uh stop making sense concert
at one point david byrne just looks at
his hand says how do i work this
what is going on
that's the quintessential question
socrates will nuances a little bit about
and ask
what is valuable what's worthwhile
what is this how is it
that we do this how is it that we make
sense of
life um
and sounds deeply you know simplistic
but
it's it's just utterly profound in the
end and again you can find folks
as you allude to the zen suchness people
um getting people to
question their presumptions getting
people to reconnect
with the simple there's a mythic
zen tail where the buddha gives a sermon
and folks are enthusiastic and want to
celebrate it and commemorate it and say
this would be a good place to erect a
temple
to build a temple and the god indra
jumps down
puts a blade of grass in the ground and
says the temple has been built
just what's happening what's always
already here spread out on the earth
thanks elf
thank you okay
we are just about coming up on our time
here
um does anybody have a final thought
final quick question
no okay i think we're good then um
well i want to thank dave for
coming to the stoa and sharing his work
with us
um if you want to know uh more about
dave the
links are in the chat
from the links you can also get his
twitter information
and more information about dave that way
and also want to thank peter and the
stoa for for hosting us and for hosting
this
conversation um it's great as always
many of you know that peter does runs
the stoa
as a gift economy uh david has put
together this talk as a kind of gift
so i know that the folks running the
show behind the scenes here would also
appreciate any gifts that you might have
in return
so i believe you can find that
information on the stoa website if you
feel so inclined
but other than that i think i think we
can wrap it there
peter did you want to close out on
anything else in the announcements or
anything
well that was spot on uh man uh you
nailed
all of it um yeah just check out the
website we had some exciting events
coming up uh
daniel schmackenberger's coming monday
to talk about metamodern stoicism
so uh i'm looking forward to that yeah
thank you david uh and adam for hosting
this excellent session
thanks everybody